Let's consider a simple vending machine where everything costs 20 cents.
我们来考虑一个简单的自动售货机 里面每样东西价格都是20分
And let's say that this vending machine only takes
假设此机器只接受5分和10分的硬币
nickels and dimes but nothing larger or smaller.
其他面额的都不接受
Then we can model the state of
那么 我们就可以为此机器的状态建立模型了
this vending machine by the amount of money that's been deposited.
具体状态是机器内存放的硬币总量
The start state would be zero cents.
开始状态是0分
And from this date there are two things that can happen.
接下来会发生两种事情
We could put in a nickel,
我们可以投入一个5分硬币
which would make the state five cents or we
此时状态变为5分
could put in a dime to take the state to 10 cents.
或者 我们投入一个10分硬币 状态变为10分
The rest of the transitions are fairly straightforward until we think about
这看起来挺简单 但是 考虑下面的情况
what to do if we are in the 15 cent state and someone puts in a dime.
机器内有15分 此刻有人投入了10分
We could just count that as 20.
我们也许会把状态变为20
But let's say that this machine requires exact change so that
但是假设此机器需要精确找零
a dime would just fall through and come
那么它就会
out of the little tray at the bottom of the machine.
把一枚5分硬币吐出到底部的小托盘里
As you can see, finite state machines are pretty straightforward conceptually.
正如大家所见 有限状态机在概念上相当简单直接
So why talk about them?
那为何我们还要讨论它？
They have their strengths and weaknesses.
因为 有限状态机有它的优点和不足
Let's start with our strengths.
我们从优点开始讨论
First, finite state machines are very easy to reason about.
首先 有限状态机非常容易推导出来
They are basically self-documenting because they map
它们的状态基本上是只看名称就能明白的
the logical state of a system directly to the physical state.
因为基本上 状态机的逻辑状态和实体机的物理状态是一一对应关系
When a nickel goes into the vending machine
当投入5分硬币
the state changes to the state that is five cents bigger than the current one.
则状态改变 当前状态加5分 就这么简单
Next, they are maintainable.
其次 有限状态机维护方便
If we wanted to tweak this machine so that everything costs
如果我们想把每件商品价格调为25分
a quarter it would be pretty trivial to just add one more state.
那么只需要略作调整 便可达到目的
Which brings us to the weaknesses of the finite state machine.
但是 这也暴露了有限状态机的不足之处
The primary one being that they are easily abused.
首先一点是 它们很容易被滥用
If they aren't designed well to begin with or if the problem
如果一开始就没设计好 或者要解决的问题有所改变
changes you can easily find yourself saying things like,
你很容易发现自己会陷入懊悔的境地
I hadn't considered that.
责怪自己当初为什么没想到一些东西
Let's just add another state and this can lead to some sloppy code and sloppy logic.
好吧 那就增加一个状态 但是这样很可能导致粗心的代码 马虎的逻辑
Which in practice means that finite state machines can be
实际上 当状态集合比较大的时候
very difficult to maintain as the states base gets bigger.
有限状态机是相当难以维护的